Ely Samuel Parker Papers 1794-1946 Mss.497.3.P223
American Philosophical Society
- Series I. Correspondence, 1794-1946; 1.5 linear feet
  - Vaccination record, 1857 Feb. 12; Bateman, Dr. (Box 4)
    Record of 54 vaccinations at Tonawanda giving age of each Indian. Names are grouped by families.
  - ANS to Ely S. Parker, 1857 Feb. 19; Smith, William F. (Box 4)
    Note stating he is pleased to have secured Ely's services for the government and will see him in Detroit March 1.
  - ADS to the United States, 1857 Mar. 14; McCarty, Michael and McCarty, Ann (Box 4)
    Deed covering sale of land for the new Marine Hospital, Galena, for the sum of $5,052.00.
  - ALS to William Parker, 1857 Mar. 18; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 4)
    Ely requests his father to give notice to the Tonawanda Band of a general council, which he will attend with Martindale to report on their success in Washington.
  - ADfS to Howell Cobb, 1857 Apr. 29; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 4)
    Draft of a letter to the Secretary of the Treasury, Washington, concerning the new Marine Hospital in Galena, covering deed for its site, progress in construction, material to be used, etc.
  - ADfS to [Howell Cobb], 1857 [April?]; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 4)
    Part of a draft of a letter concerning stone for the Custom House in Galena.
  - ALS to Howell Cobb, 1857 May 7; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 4)
    Letter acknowledging communications from the Secretary of the Treasury, Washington, concerning the construction of public buildings in Galena.
  - ALS to [Howell Cobb], 1857 May 11; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 4)
    Acknowledgment of the Secretary of the Treasurer's reply to Ely's letter of April 29 [q.v.].
  - ALS to [Howell Cobb], 1857 May 11; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 4)
    Acknowledgments of the Secretary of the Treasurer's letters of May 5th and 6th concerning Custom House lot and estimates.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1857 June 6; Blair, Lewis H. (Box 4)
    A chatty letter, with references to mutual friends in Detroit.
  - ALS to Lewis H. Blair, 1857 June 9; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 4)
    A reply to Blair's letter, containing an unflattering description of Westerners.
  - Tonawanda Chiefs, 1857 June 16 (Box 4)
    Power of attorney for John H. Martindale, Isaac Verplank, and Ely S. Parker, to transact business with officials of the U.S. Government in Washington. Signed by 23 chiefs, warriors, etc.
  - AMs to J.W. Dewer, 1857 June 30; Parker, Ely S.; Martindale, John H.; Bryan, William G.; and Follett, Frederick (Box 4)
    An outline of the measures suggested by the Tonawanda delegation as a means of settling the Indians' dispute with the Ogden Co.
  - New York Herald, 1857 July 6 (Box 4)
    Newspaper clipping concerning the object of the Tonawanda delegation in Washington, which includes Ely S. Parker, F. Follett, W.C. Bryan and J.H. Martindale.
  - ALS to F.E. Geiger, 1857 July 8; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 4)
    Draft of a letter listing enclosed drawings for Customs House and Marine Hospital.
  - ALS to [Howell Cobb], 1857 July 9; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 4)
    Report of operations for May and June on the new Customs House, Galena, Ill., to the Secretary of the Treasury, Washington, D.C.
  - ALS to [Howell Cobb], 1857 July 9; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 4)
    Construction report for April, May and June, on the new Marine Hospital, Galena, Ill., to the Secretary of the Treasury, Washington, D.C.
  - ALS to [Howell Cobb], 1857 July 24; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 4)
    Draft of a letter to the Secretary of the Treasury, concerning estimated cost of constructing the foundation for the new Customs House.
  - ALS to A.E. Brenizer, 1857 Aug. 18-19; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 4)
    Newspaper clipping of a report to the Chairman of the Committee on Lock and Dam, concerning the quantity of water available for, and the estimated cost of constructing a lock on the Galena River, together with brief editorial comment on same.
  - ALS to [Ely S. Parker], 1857 Sept. 23; Anderson, Robert (Box 4)
    Form letter concerning material ordered from Cooper, Hewitt and Co. of New York for the Galena Custom House.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1857 Oct. 12; Cart[?] (Box 4)
    Letter from a friend in Leavenworth, Kansas, discussing the slavery issue, corrupt politics, etc.
  - Invoice, 1857 Oct. 27; Geiger, Frederick E. (Box 4)
    Bill for labor and materials in excavating cisterns in Galena.
  - DS with United States, Galena (Ill.) (Box 4)
    Part of an agreement between the city of Galena, Ill., and the U.S.A. for a plot of ground fronting on Green, Water and Commerce Streets, in Galena.
  - ALS to Charles E. Mix, 1857 [Nov. 17] 1857 Oct. 28; Parker, Ely S.; Parker, Nicholson H.; Martindale, J.H.; Bryan, William G.; and Follett, Frederick (Box 4)
    Draft of an agreement between the Tonawanda delegation and the Commissioner of Indian Affairs, providing for purchase of the Indians' lands from the Ogden Co. out of funds put aside by the U.S. Government for the Indians' removal and support West of the Missouri.
  - Politics and its corruptions in northwestern Illinois, 1857 [Nov. 2]; Jackson, R. H. (Box 4)
    Printed copy of an address, on pp. 7-8 of which are the speaker's remarks in defense of Ely S. Parker as Superintendent of Public Works in Galena.
  - New York Evening Express, 1857 Nov. 5 (Box 4)
    Typewritten copy of a newspaper clipping from the issue of January 9, 1858, concerning the Treaty of Nov. 5, 1857, between the Tonawandas and the U.S. Government, in settlement of the Ogden land dispute.
  - Census of Tonawanda Band, 1857 Nov.?; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 4)
    Census of the Tonawanda Band by heads of families.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1857 Dec. 7; Parker, Nicholson H. (Box 4)
    Letter concerning details of an annuity payment at Tonawanda. B.H. Colgrove has been appointed agent for the New York Indians.
  - ALS to Charles Hendrie, 1857 Dec. 25; Geiger, Frederick E. (Box 4)
    Agreement covering transfer of contract dated Mar. 25, 1857, for the construction of Custom House, Post Office and Marine Hospital at Galena, Ill.
  - Specifications for building the Custom-House and Post Office, at Galena, Ill., U.S. Treasury Department. Office of the Construction of Buildings (Box 4)
    Printed item.
  - Specifications for building the Marine Hospital at Galena, Illinois, U.S. Treasury Department. Office of the Construction of Buildings (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous memoranda, [1857-59]; 7 sheets.; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 4)
    Miscellaneous memoranda concerning plans, work, and expenditures on public buildings in Galena.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1858 Jan. 18; Cole, S. (Box 4)
    Note from the Pension Office re. the issuance of a new pension certificate for William Parker.
  - Invalid pension certificate, 1858 Jan. 19; U.S. Department of the Interior (Box 4)
    Invalid Pension Certificate authorizing payments of $8.00 a month to William Parker.
  - Quarterly return, 1858 Mar. 31; Galena (Ill.). Custom House (Box 4)
    Quarterly return of materials, machinery, etc. for the Custom House and Marine Hospital, Galena, Ill.
  - ALS to Charles H. Sherrill, 1858 Apr. 9; Wilkeson and Co. (Box 4)
    Receipt for $24.75 covering cost of publication in Albany Journal of notice that sealed proposals for work on the Erie Canal must be received at the Commissioner's office by Apr. 5.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1858 May 24; Edwards, Howard (Box 4)
    A letter from a friend in Philadelphia advising that he has obtained a facsimile of the Penn Wampum Belt, which he would like to deliver to Ely in person, and asking where he can obtain a copy of the poem "Yonondio" by W.H.C. Hosmer.
  - Census of Tonawanda Band, 1858 May 24; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 4)
    Census, by head of family, giving number of men, women, children, deaths, etc.
  - Memoranda, 1858 July 31 and Aug. 5; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 4)
    Memoranda as to money expended by Frederick E. Geiger in the construction of the Custom House and Marine Hospital, Galena.
  - ALS to N.B. Matthews, 1858 Aug. 20; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 4)
    Brief letter concerning Joseph Follows' reply to Ely's inquiry as to the terms on which the Ogden Co. would dispose of "the right, title and interest in and to the Allegany Reservation."
  - ALS to Charles Hendrie, 1858 Sept. 14; Joice, [I. F.]?. (Box 4)
    Bill for $65.00 for labor on Custom House, Galena.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1858 Oct. 4; Parker, Nicholson H. (Box 4)
    Because of prejudice against their `system' there will be no students from Cattaraugus for the `Catholic college,' but Father Doran has visited Tonawanda to interview prospective students from there. At a council held at Cattaraugus to discuss the Kansas land claims of New York Indians, it was decided to send 2 delegates from each tribe to Washington.
  - ALS to William Donald Noble, 1858 Oct. 13; Jennings, Joseph C. (Box 4)
    Copy of a letter from the Superintendent of the new Custom House, at Nauvoo, Ill., to the foreman of Bostater and Fents, notifying him to suspend quarrying operations and to turn over lists in his possession concerning dimensions of required stone.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1858 Nov. 24; Hendrie, Charles (Box 4)
    Notice of transfer and sale of goods in possession of John Lorrain, on behalf of F.E. Geiger, for use in the construction of Custom House and Marine Hospital, Galena.
  - Memorandum, 1858 Dec. 17; [Parker, Ely S.] (Box 4)
    Memorandum concerning stone work completed by Bostater and Fents prior to receiving instructions to suspend operations.
  - ALS to Levi Lusk, 1858 Dec. 27; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 4)
    A request that Lusk address a meeting of the Miner's Lodge, Galena, on January 7.
  - ADS to H. H. Gear, 1859 Jan. 13; Parker, Ely S.; Jones, J. R.; and Morehurst, D. B. (Box 5)
    Notification that Gear has been elected an honorary member of Miner's Lodge.
  - ALS to [Ely S. Parker], 1859 Feb. 26; Edwards, Howard (Box 5)
    Note stating he has mailed a copy of Boudinot's "Star in the West" to Ely at Pembroke.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1859 Apr. 5; Parker, Caroline (Box 5)
    Martindale has not yet been to Tonawanda to help settle matters connected with the Indians' purchase of their land. Newton spent four weeks at Cattaraugus, but failed to come home `to see his boy' because the family have not written to him. Caroline has received another letter from Mr. Hurd.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1859 Apr. 9; [Cobb, Howell] (Box 5)
    Letter referring to a quarrel between the partners, Bostater and Fents, contractors for the Dubuque Custom House, and enclosing correspondence "unofficially forwarded" to keep the Superintendent advised.
  - ADS to Miners' Lodge, Galena, 1859 Apr. 12; Marble and Smith (Box 5)
    Written bid for carpentry and other work on Lodge room in Mitchell's Hall.
  - Invoice to Miners' Lodge No. 273, Galena, 1859 Apr. 15; Hunkin, W. and Snider, S. (Box 5)
    Bill totalling $689.50 for fitting up Mitchell's Hall as a Lodge room.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1859 May 11; Taylor, Henry H. (Box 5)
    Note enclosing a Lodge "petition."
  - ADS to Ely S. Parker, 1859 May 16 and June 1; Marble and Smith (Box 5)
    Receipts for $100 and $75 for labor in fitting up Mitchell's Hall, Calena, as a Masonic lodge room.
  - ADS to E.S. Parker, 1859 May 22; Collins, E. A., Sons and Co. (Box 5)
    Receipted bill for cloth.
  - ADS to Ely S. Parker, 1859 May 23; Porter and Spratt (Box 5)
    Receipt for $83.80 covering carpet for Miner's Lodge.
  - ADS to Ely S. Parker, 1859 June 11; Smith and Allen (Box 5)
    Recipt for $30.00 for painting and papering Miner's Lodge.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1859 June 13; Morse, H. P. (Box 5)
    Letter concerning a price list and order for Masonic goods.
  - ADS to E.S. Parker, 1859 July 2 and 6; Marble and Smith (Box 5)
    Receipt and bill for carpentry work, etc. on Miner's Lodge.
  - ADS to Masonic Lodge, 1859 July 5 and 6; Smith and Allen (Box 5)
    Receipted bills for painting, papering, etc.
  - ADS to Masonic Lodge, 1859 Aug. 3; Smith and Holmes (Box 5)
    Receipted bill for $4.00.
  - Memorandum, 1859 Sept. 1; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 5)
    Memorandum of payments on contract, etc. Dubuque Custom House.
  - ALS to M. B., 1859 Oct. 2; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 5)
    Letter to an old friend, explaining an unfilled promise to call on her [?] and Mr. and Mrs. Colman when he was in New York in August.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1859 Oct. 21; Hendrie, Charles (Box 5)
    Letter inquiring when the final settlement will be made for work on the Custom House and Marine Hospital, Galena.
  - Wrappers, 1859 Oct. 25; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 5)
    Three mail wrappers addressed to Ely at Galena, Ill.
  - ALS to Charles Hendrie, 1859 Oct. 26; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 5)
    Reply stating he expects to render a final statement to Washington in a week or ten days and that he must first carry out instructions "to examine the accounts of the contractors" to determine the amount due Mr. Geiger for his share of the construction of the public buildings in Galena.
  - AMsS, 1859 [Oct.?]; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 5)
    Statement of quantities and specifications for grading and paving the Custom House grounds in Galena and for furnishing the building ready for occupancy.
  - ALS to Howell Cobb, 1859 Nov. 14; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 5)
    Request for approval of the appointment of William Davis as watchman at the Galena Marine Hospital.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1859 Nov. 23; McGenniss, J. W. (Box 5)
    A reply to Ely's inquiry, from the Secretary of the Illinois Stone Co., Chicago, enclosing a printed price list.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1859 Nov. 24; Mitchell, W. N. (Box 5)
    Letter written on Illinois State Penitentiary stationery, advising that Messrs. Sawyer and Carey, the Superintendent and Warden, will write Ely "upon the subject of stone." Ely is invited to Joliet to dedicate a new Masonic Hall on Dec. 27.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1859 Dec. 20; Dennison, William (Box 5)
    Letter advising that Samuel B. Leaken of Galena has been authorized to act for the writer in collecting an amount due him from Mr. Geiger.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1860 Jan. 11; Parker, William H. (Box 5)
    Martindale wants Ely to go to Albany with him to have legislation passed empowering Tonawanda chiefs to arrest, and fine or imprison, Indians who sell timber to Whites. There has been quarreling on the reservation over occupancy of houses vacated by the Whites. Levi has been quite sick.
  - ADS to Ely S. Parker, 1860 Jan. 16; Morris and Monsarrat (Box 5)
    Acknowledgment of a remittance for $2 to cover subscription to "The Voice of Masonry..." to be sent to W.R. Rowley and J.B. Booth of Galena.
  - Wrapper to Ely S. Parker, 1860 [Jan. 31?]; Rodman, G. (Box 5)
    Mail wrapper addressed to Ely at Dubuque.
  - ALS to James E. Stewart, 1860 Feb. 12; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 5)
    Letter returning Stewart's clain against F.E. Geiger, advising there is no balance due Geiger from his partner in connection with the construction of public buildings in Galena.
  - ALS to A. B. Greenwood, 1860 Mar. 29; Thompson, J. (Box 5)
    Copy of a reply from the Secretary of the Department of the Interior to the Commissioner of Indian Affairs, concerning the claims of New York Indians to land in Kansas Territory. The Secretary concurs that the provisions of the Treaty of 1838 should apply only to those Indians living in New York in 1838 and settled in Kansas on March 21, 1859. The claims of Indians not on "the census list submitted by Special Agent Stevens" need not be investigated.
  - ALS to Howell Cobb, 1860 Apr. 6; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 5)
    Note requesting approval of sale of an unused furnace, stove, etc. at Galena Custom House.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1860 Apr. 7; Bruff, William H. (Box 5)
    Note discussing Lodge accounts and other details.
  - Royal Arch Masonic membership certificate, 1860 Apr. 7; Hall, Edwin Robert (Box 5)
    Certificate signed by the Secretary of the Chapter at Rochester that "Ely S. Parker is... a Royal Arch Mason in good and regular standing."
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1860 Apr. 18; Smith, J. C. (Box 5)
    Letter from a fellow Mason accepting Ely's offer to superintend carpentry work on Dubuque Custom House, with references to mutual friends.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1860 May 10; Ranney, Henry C. (Box 5)
    Letter inquiring if Ely will attend a masonic meeting in Chicago on May 17.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1860 May 17; Parker, Nicholson H. (Box 5)
    Letter concerning the purchase of land at Tonawanda by the Parker family. Fifty acres have been added to Ely's farm, as compensation to the Grand Sachem for his services. Nick states it has always been his intention to return to Tonawanda some day and that he has made no permanent settlement at Cattaraugus.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1860 June 7; Harstock, James R. and Parvin, Theodore S. (Box 5)
    Certificate, signed by the Grand Master and Grand Secretary of the Grand Lodge of Iowa, appointing Ely S. Parker a representative "to strengthen ties of brotherly affection" etc. between the Iowa and Illinois lodges.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1860 Aug. 4; Burke, William H. (Box 5)
    A letter outlining the Grand Master B.B. French's directions for "forming around the triangle in military order."
  - ALS to G. C. Clark, 1860 Sept. 19; Kendrick, E. E. (Box 5)
    Notification from the Cashier of the Bank of Albany that William Parker's pension for $47.75 has been received.
  - ALS to [Ely S.] Parker, 1860 Sept. 30; Parker, Caroline (Box 5)
    Letter asking for advice about renting to an individual who "wants to sow wheat on our old place..."
  - ALS to Miners' Lodge No. 273, 1860 [Nov. 1?]; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 5)
    A draft list of accusations against W. Spalding, a member of the Lodge.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1860 Dec. 1; Lancaster, A. (Box 5)
    Receipt from Great Western Dispatch for freight charges on 69 boxes of glass.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1860 Dec. 30; Smith, J. C. (Box 5)
    List of items, broken or damaged, in shipment of glass for new Custom House, Dubuque.
  - ALS to R.G. Corwin, 1860 Dec. 6; Bryant, D. (Box 5)
    Request that Corwin support Bryant's recommendation of I.G. Palmer for Postmaster at Urbana.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1861 Jan. 8; [Smith, J. C.]? (Box 5)
    Statement of mouldings required to complete work on the new Custom House, Dubuque.
  - ALS Smith to Ely S. Parker, 1861 Jan. 26; Smith, Marcus W. (Box 5)
    Receipted bill for clothing bought between Sept. and Jan.
  - ALS to Westphal and Hinds, 1861 Jan. 30; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 5)
    Authorization to deliver to bearer materials for Dubuque Custom House.
  - ALS to Elias S. Terry, 1861 Feb. 12; New York Indians in Kansas Territory (Box 5)
    Notarized power-of-attorney in prosecuting claims under treaties of 1838 and 1842. Document bears names and marks of 12 chiefs.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1861 Mar. 13; Burke, M. T. (Box 5)
    An invitation, written at the request of Brother Hunkins, to attend a meeting of the Miner's Lodge, Galena, on Mar. 15.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1861 Apr. 11; Chan, S. P. (Box 5)
    Acknowledgment by the Secretary of the Treasury of Ely's report of operations for March at the Dubuque Custom House.
  - ALS to Clark B. Cochrane, 1861 July 2; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 5)
    A request for blank forms and instructions for filling in same for "Invalid Pensioners."
  - ALS to G.C. Clark, 1861 Sept. 14; Parker, William H. (Box 5)
    Power-of-attorney authorizing G.C. Clark to collect at Albany a pension payment for the period March 4 to September 4, 1861.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1862 Feb. 6; Mix, Charles E. (Box 5)
    A letter from the Acting Commissioner of Indian Affairs "enclosing an Act of the Legislature of the State of New York authorizing the Comptroller...to hold the Tonawanda Indian Reservation in trust...as contamplated by the treaty of March 31, 1859."
  - ALS to Nicholson H. Parker, 1862 Feb. 23; 1p.; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 5)
    Letter concerning illness, death and funeral of Elizabeth Parker, "our dear and beloved mother."
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1862 Mar. 12; Dole, William P. (Box 5)
    A letter from the Commissioner of Indian Affairs, replying to Ely's inquiry of the 5th, advising there is nothing to prevent the Indians from volunteering for war service, but that "there is nothing compulsory in the matter."
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1862 Apr. 4; 2p.; Fisk, John (Box 5)
    Typewritten copy of a letter advising that the Mustering Officer at Buffalo has received belated instructions to enroll 300 Indian recruits, and that in this connection, Capt. Jemison will visit Tonawanda, probably accompanied by Cusick and the writer.
  - ALS to New York (State), 1862 May 25; 3p.; Hull, F. H. (Box 5)
    Copy of a bill for $35.40, rendered by the Sheriff of Genessee County, for serving eviction notices to 12 White settlers on the Tonawanda Reservation, at the request of District Attorney, James M. Willett.
  - ALS to Horatio Ballard, 1862 June 17; 1p.; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 5)
    Letter to the Secretary of State, Albany, asking to be kept informed about the proposed proceedings of the Seneca Nation at Cattaraugus and Allegany "to enjoin the Seneca state annuity."
  - Petitition, 1862 [June?]; 2p.; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 5)
    Part of a petition or letter concerning the appropriation, by the Seneca Nation at Cattaraugus and Allegany, of the whole of the $500 state annuity provided by the Treaty of 1815, thus robbing the Tonawandas of their equitable share.
  - ALS to L.L. Doty, 1862 July 21; 1p.; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 5)
    A brief note in which Ely states "your synopsis of Cusick's traditions...is admirably done," and apologises for the delay in replying to other questions returned with the letter.
  - ALS to E. S. Terry, 1862 Sept. 24; 1p.; Mix, Charles E. (Box 5)
    An acknowledgment from the Acting Commissioner of Indian Affairs of the Memorial on behalf of the New York Indians in Kansas Territory which "will doubtless be submitted to Congress."
  - Notes, 1862 Dec. 1; [Wright, Asher?] (Box 5)
    Pencilled notes in leather bound memo book on the Council of the Six Nations held at Cattaraugus, Dec. 1-2, 1862 with the names and remarks of the attending chiefs.
  - ADS to Isaac Shanks, 1863 May 23; Moses, William (Box 5)
    Permit to lease 6 acres of his improvement to Whites, signed by the "President" of a council of Tonawanda chiefs, and attested by Ely S. Parker, "Clerk." Freeman Guide 3370.
  - [Batavia] Newspaper, 1863 [July?] (Box 5)
    News item concerning a council at Tonawanda to bid farewell to Ely S. Parker who has joined Grant's army.
  - AL to Martha [Hoyt Parker], 1863 Aug. 15; Parker, Newton I. (Box 5)
    A letter about life with the 132nd Regt. N.Y. Infantry, stationed near Newbern, N.C. Newton asks to be remembered to relatives and friends and promises to dwell on other topics in a future letter which Martha can read "when all our little papooses are asleep." The letter is written in a hand unlike Newton Parker's.
  - ALS to N. H. Parker, 1863 Oct. 7; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 5)
    Letter acknowledging receipt of news from Carrie that William Parker is sick and not expected to recover, and advising Nic to move with his family to Tonawanda as Carrie "cannot take care of everything."
  - ALS to N. H. Parker, 1863 Nov. 18; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 5)